welcome to the listening Time Podcast
hey everybody this is Connor and you're
listening to
episode 140 of the listening Time
Podcast I hope you're all doing great
today I hope that your brain is in
English mode and that you're ready to
practice your listening and in today's
episode we're going to talk about a
really interesting and relevant topic
for all of you I think you'll all
appreciate this one we're going to talk
about why it seems so hard to go from an
intermediate to an advanced level in
English or in any other language of
course but since you're learning English
I'm using that language as an example so
we'll talk about why the process see
seems so difficult to go from an
intermediate English learner and speaker
to an advanced English speaker so why is
that uh we're going to talk about that
today and I'll offer some
suggestions about how to uh help you out
with that process these tips aren't
going to solve all of your problems
instantly
of course but I think that they can help
so we'll talk about that today and
before we start remember that if you
want to practice with my Advanced
episodes in which I speak fast make sure
to become a listening Time family member
the link is in the description below
this episode that's
patreon.com time and if you want my new
podcast my us conversations podcast in
which which I talk to people from all
over the us about different topics and
provide the transcript and the
definitions of key words and phrases
that we use then make sure to sign up
for that the link is also in the
description below this episode that's
patreon.com uson conversations and as
always please share this podcast with
your friends and family members and
please give it a five star rating on
Spotify or apple podcasts and write a
review all right let's get started are
your ears ready you know what time it is
it's listening
time okay so let's talk about why it's
so hard uh once you reach an
intermediate level in English or any
other language so I'm going to talk
about the main re reason in my opinion
there are multiple reasons of course but
I want to focus on the really big one uh
the one that really um makes a
difference uh in the process when you're
a beginner or an intermediate learner so
I'm sure you've felt this before if
you're already at an intermediate level
you've probably felt the difference
between when you first uh started
learning English maybe not at the very
beginning because you probably learned
in high school in those terrible classes
so just ignore that but maybe uh as an
adult or whatever when you started
learning more
seriously uh it might have seemed like
like you were
improving uh relatively quickly uh when
you started dedicating time to learning
English uh but once you reach an
intermediate level this progress seems
to slow down a lot and right now uh I'm
learning Italian as I mentioned in the
last episode and I started from scratch
from zero and it seems like I'm learning
a ton of things uh right now but I know
that once I reach an intermediate level
in Italian I will also feel this
progress slow down a lot it's going to
happen to me so I'm just enjoying the
beginning stages when it's really fun
and I feel like I'm learning a lot so
I'm sure sure a lot of you have felt
this before and you might wonder why
well the main reason why in my opinion
is because of the
frequency of the words that you're
seeing that you're hearing or reading so
the 100 most common words in
English uh they come up they
appear much much more
frequently than the next uh 100 words or
the next uh 1,000 words or whatever so
why is that important so the words that
are the most common in a language like
English are very very common you can't
uh
construct many sentences uh without
these words so they show up over and
over and over again in all types of
sentences it doesn't matter what the
subject is who's talking where the
person is from these words are going to
show up time and time again from the
first day that you start learning
English so when you first start you're
going to see these common words again
and again and you're going to learn them
pretty quickly because they're
repeated just over and over again and
that helps you to learn them fast they
become essential words for you so for
example uh the
wordthe in
English that's an extremely common word
one of the most common words and you
can't really say much at all without
that word that word is everywhere so you
probably learned the
wordthe very quickly uh without even
trying uh what's another example maybe
the word
and or the word
because these are function words that
are so incredibly
necessary uh to the language that they
show up
in many many sentences so you're going
to learn them no matter what in English
when we say the phrase no matter what
we're saying with no exceptions it's
definitely going to happen so you're
going to learn words like and and the
the and because no matter what you can't
uh get very far without those words so
this is great because when we first
start learning a language uh these words
show up time and time again and you
learn them really quickly and you
quickly go from zero words to 100 words
or whatever because uh you've seen those
words so many times you've gotten so
much repetition with those words so that
means that you can go from zero to a
high beginner or low intermediate level
relatively quickly uh because you're
going to establish the basics of English
pretty quickly as long as you practice
as long as you dedicate
some time and energy to this and you're
going to establish these Basics with the
foundation of these common words right
if you have those 100 common words or
200 most common words in English you're
going to have some Foundation to build
upon and that's great however once you
reach that high beginner level level or
that low intermediate level probably
what's going to happen is that you
already have those common words they're
already in your
brain and now you don't have many other
really common words uh that are new for
you so the words that are new now are
words that are are less common much less
common so they aren't going to show up
very often you're not going to get a lot
of repetition and exposure to those
words so for example let's take the word
frame uh this is that thing uh where you
put a picture so that you can hang it on
the wall or put it on your desk it's
that square or rectangular thing around
a picture that's the frame so that's
something that a lot of us uh or most of
us have in our houses it's a pretty
common object if you think about it
right a picture frame that's something
you see
everywhere however do you really hear
that that word every day absolutely not
do you even hear that word once a week
or even once a
month probably not unless you're someone
who works with pictures and frames you
probably don't even hear that word more
than once a month so it's going to be a
lot harder for you to remember the word
frame than it would will be to remember
the word because and that's because of
the frequency of these words so once
you're at this intermediate level and
you have the
basics everything that is new or that
isn't very familiar to you is going to
show up and then go away and you don't
know when you're going to see it again
unfortunately so you see a word and then
you try to memorize that word okay frame
and then you don't see that word again
for two months and then by that time
you've already forgotten what it means
and then it shows up again and you think
hm that word looks familiar but I don't
remember what it means and then you have
to look it up again this happen happens
to me all the time it happens to me
constantly and it's very very
frustrating because many times you even
recognize the word and say hey I
remember learning this word I remember
looking up the meaning but I still don't
remember what it means and because of
that you have to look it up again and
you're probably going to forget forg get
it again and so this is just a
reality once you reach an intermediate
level you're not going to see all of
these new words very frequently so it's
going to feel like you're making much
less progress uh you're not learning as
much as you did when you first started
you're not going to understand a lot of
things because a lot of words will be
said that you don't know well yet maybe
you've heard them before but you haven't
heard them
repeated hundreds or thousands of times
like you have with the words and and for
and because Etc so progress is going to
seem very slow and you're going to be
improving as long as you keep on
practicing because of course you're
still solidifying the basics to solidify
something means that you establish it
with more strength right you'll still be
solidifying the basics and you'll still
be getting that exposure to new words
and phrases but uh it will be very slow
you won't get as much repetition so it
will take you a lot longer to learn
these other words uh and it won't seem
like you're improving you are like I
mentioned but it seems much much
slower and so that's not very fun
obviously uh but that's kind of the
reality of languages and I've even seen
a statistic
I can't verify if it's true or not but I
think if it's not true it's probably
pretty close to the truth and that is
that the 100 most frequent words in
English make up
50% of all of what you will read in
English when I use the phrasal verb make
up in this context I'm saying that they
comprise right uh they comprise 50% of
all written English so imagine that the
100 most frequent words in English will
be about
50% of everything that you see uh when
you read and maybe even when you hear
people speak English so that means that
all the other thousands and thousands of
words in English are only uh that other
50% so uh you can see how uh
infrequent those other words are going
to be when you're learning English right
so that statistic just shows the reality
of a word frequency and why that makes
it so hard once you've reached an
intermediate level but what can you do
to not solve this but to help you out
with this process uh if you're already
at a lower intermediate level and you
feel like progress is slow what can you
do well I thought of four things uh that
you can do the first one is the one
that's uh not the most interesting or
fun and that is simply to dedicate more
time uh to your language learning uh
Prim arily uh listening and reading and
having conversations so I thought of
this because I have a
student uh who might be listening to
this episode I don't know but this
student spends 4 hours a day Listening
to English that's a lot he spends 3
hours actively listening and another
hour passively listening while he's
multitasking and doing something else so
the simple fact that he is listening so
much gives him enough
repetition to hear the less frequent
words more often because most of us most
of us language Learners do not spend 4
hours listening we might spend one hour
listening and some of us us might only
spend 30 minutes listening or maybe this
podcast is your only listening today and
this is what 25 30 minutes maybe 25
minutes uh so if you compare that to 4
hours uh that's a big
difference so the repetition of less
frequent words uh won't be very high if
you're only listening for 30 minutes a
day but if you're listening for 4 hours
a day uh those words that are new uh the
less common words will actually show up
more often and that will give you a
chance to learn them faster so it's
pretty simple obviously and most of us
uh probably aren't G to find three or
four hours uh just to dedicate to
listening uh so that might not be the
easiest thing for most of us but I
wanted to mention it because my student
does this and it works great for him
he's improved a ton even at the
intermediate level so another way uh
another thing that can help you with
this process is to use spaced
repetition so there are many tools
available online and a lot of them are
free that are designed to help you uh
study words or whatever phrases
sentences or things from other subjects
not just language learning um they help
you um practice memorizing these things
and then they will show you a certain
word when you're probably about to
forget it so these spaced repetition
apps uh and websites are designed to
help you get really good
repetition of new
words and you can put in your new words
or new phrases uh and they will show
these uh flash cards to you and you can
practice with them and uh they will show
you the same word at the uh optimal time
the perfect time before you're going to
forget it or right when you're
forgetting that word and this is a very
scientific approach based on uh how we
forget things so apps and sites like
Inky a Ki this is a fantastic tool that
you can use uh to help you out with that
of course it's going to require some
effort you have to input words uh that
you want to remember that you want to
learn you're going to have to take some
time to do that and to study these words
but it's a way that you can get more
repetition of new words that you want to
learn so that's another thing you can do
and the third thing you can do is to use
normal repetition methods uh like what I
always propose uh that you do with this
podcast or any other content that you
consume um that you listen multiple
times to the same episode or the same
content right so you can listen to this
episode
three times or four times or five
times and when you do that uh you're
going to get a lot of
repetition of words and phrases that
you're unfamiliar with or that you're
not quite comfortable with so if you
listen to this episode five times then
one of the new words that I used here is
going to replay five
times uh into your ears and that's much
more powerful than if you only hear it
one time so that's pretty obvious right
so that's something pretty easy that you
can do and I have one other tip that I
think will really help you it's
something that I incorporate into my l
language learning and that is that I
spend periods of time listening to
content about the same subject so for
example I might spend uh a full month
listening to content
specifically about uh let's say online
business right and I listen to
multiple uh podcast tasts and watch
multiple different YouTube channels uh
that are all about this same subject and
because they're all about the same
subject I hear them use very similar
terminology and phrases and things like
that uh these words and phrases show up
again and again and again because
they're very useful phrases uh and words
for this topic and then maybe the next
month I might spend more time uh
listening to content about personal
development and then a lot of the same
words and phrases show up if I keep
listening to content about that topic
and so you can kind of cycle through
different topics like this and consume a
lot of content content uh about these
topics and that will help you uh get
more
repetition uh with certain words and
certain phrases and then you move on to
another topic uh I really like doing
this and I also like doing this with the
same person the same YouTuber or
podcaster because people tend to uh use
the same words
we all have our own speaking style so uh
we repeat the same words and phrases
over and over again and so I might spend
a month uh really focusing on one
podcast for example and I'll hear this
podcaster say the same things time and
time again and it really helps me get
that repetition for certain words and
phrases that that person says and then
I'll switch to another podcaster or
YouTuber and they say different words uh
and phrases that I'm not familiar with
and then I get a lot of repetition with
those ones so you see how that can work
right uh that's something that I've
found uh to be very useful for me so
those are four things that I was able to
think of um there are more and I'm sure
I'll do many more episodes in the future
about language learning and different
tips and things like that but I just
wanted to share those ones today I hope
this episode was interesting for you and
I hope it encourages you to keep on
practicing even if the progress seems
slow and one way you can practice is by
by using my Advanced podcast episodes so
if you're interested in that make sure
to click on the link in the episode
description that's
patreon.com
listeningtime and another way you can
practice is with my conversations that I
have with other native speakers so if
you're interested in that sign up for my
us conversations podcast the link is
also down below that's
patreon.com USC conversations and as
always please share this podcast with
anyone else you know who might find it
useful and please give it a five-star
rating on Spotify Apple podcasts or
wherever and write a review all right
thank you for listening to this episode
and I'll talk to you on the next episode
of listening
time